Edna O'Brien papers, circa 1939-2000
Emory University
- Writings by O'Brien, ca. 1953-1999, Series 3; Boxes 27-78; OP1
  - Prose, 1960-1999, Subseries 3.2; Boxes 28-59
    - A Wife, Notebook (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - Nonfiction Essays and Short Pieces
    - "The Artist and His Country," TS (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - "The Bishop's Bonfire," TS (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - "Books of the Year," TS (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - "The Celtic Muse in Irish Literature," TS (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - "Charlotte Bronte," TS (Box 57, Folder 5)
    - "Clothes," TS (Box 57, Folder 6)
    - "County Clare," TS (Box 57, Folder 7)
    - "Cuba," TS (Box 57, Folder 8)
    - "Dear Mr. Joyce," TS and Proof (Box 57, Folder 9)
    - "Dubhlinn," TS (Box 57, Folder 10)
    - "Dublin," MS, TS, and Proof (Box 57, Folder 11)
    - "Dubliners," TS (Box 57, Folder 12)
    - "Faulkner," MS, TS, and Proof (Box 57, Folder 13)
    - "Food for Thought," TS and Proof (Box 57, Folder 14)
    - "Forgiveness," TS (Box 57, Folder 15)
    - "Friendship," TS (Box 57, Folder 16)
    - "Going Back to Clare," TS (Box 57, Folder 17)
    - "Going Solo," TS and Proof [variant title: "Travelling Alone"] (Box 57, Folder 18)
    - "Inside Ulster," TS (Box 57, Folder 19)
    - "Introduction for Edna O'Brien's Short Stories," TS (Box 57, Folder 20)
    - "Intuition," TS (Box 57, Folder 21)
    - "Irish Dreams," TS, Color MS [proof with original correspondence] (Box 57, Folder 22)
    - "Jaw-Jaw," MS and TS (Box 57, Folder 23)
    - "Kiss and Tell, TS (Box 57, Folder 24)
    - "Lunch with Mr. Joyce," TS [variant title: "Lunch with the Sirens"] (Box 57, Folder 25)
    - "Memory," Notebook (Box 57, Folder 26)
    - "Men I Have Loved," Galley proof (Box 57, Folder 27)
    - "My Day," TS (Box 57, Folder 28)
    - "Northern Ireland," TS (Box 57, Folder 29)
    - "One Day in the World," TS (Box 57, Folder 30)
    - "Power," TS (Box 57, Folder 31)
    - "Proust and the Ritz," TS (Box 57, Folder 32)
    - "The Public and the Private Self," TS (Box 58, Folder 1)
    - "Pubs," TS (Box 58, Folder 2)
    - "Return to Dublin," TS (Box 58, Folder 3)
    - "Samuel Beckett at 80," TS (Box 58, Folder 4)
    - "Somewhere Over the Rainbow," TS (Box 58, Folder 5)
    - "St. Patrick's Day," TS (Box 58, Folder 6)
    - "Stop Street," TS (Box 58, Folder 7)
    - "The Strange World of Carson McCullers," TS (Box 58, Folder 8)
    - "Sweet Are the Uses of Adversity," TS (Box 58, Folder 9)
    - "The Tolstoy Saga," MS and TS (Box 58, Folder 10)
    - "The Tolostoy Sonata," TS (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - "The Truth about Vietnam," TS (Box 58, Folder 12)
    - "Ulster Pieces," MS and TS (Box 58, Folder 13)
    - "Ulster Pieces," Research material (Box 58, Folder 14)
    - "Ulster Pieces," Research material (Box 58, Folder 15)
    - "Virginia," TS (Box 58, Folder 16)
    - "The Way We Read Now," TS (Box 58, Folder 17)
    - "West of Ireland," TS (Box 58, Folder 18)
    - "Who is Writing This," TS (Box 58, Folder 19)
    - "Why I Love Short Stories," TS (Box 58, Folder 20)
    - "Women In Literature," TS and Research material (Box 58, Folder 21)
    - "Women's Letters," TS (Box 58, Folder 22)
    - "The Writing Life," TS (Box 58, Folder 23)
    - Untitled lecture, MS and TS (Box 58, Folder 24)
    - Untitled (Box 58, Folder 25)
    - Book-Length Nonfiction
    - Mother Ireland (1976)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 58, Folder 26)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 58, Folder 27)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 58, Folder 28)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 58, Folder 29)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 58, Folder 30)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 58, Folder 31)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 58, Folder 32)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 58, Folder 33)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 58, Folder 34)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 1)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 2)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 3)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 4)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 5)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 6)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 7)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 8)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 9)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 10)
    - Mother Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 11)
    - Mother Ireland, Research material (Box 59, Folder 12)
    - James and Nora: A Portrait of Joyce's Marriage (1981)
    - James and Nora, Proof (Box 59, Folder 13)
    - Vanishing Ireland (1987)
    - Vanishing Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 14)
    - Vanishing Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 15)
    - Vanishing Ireland, TS (Box 59, Folder 16)
    - James Joyce (1999)
    - James Joyce, MS and TS (Box 59, Folder 17)
    - James Joyce, TS (Box 59, Folder 18)
    - James Joyce, TS (Box 59, Folder 19)
    - James Joyce, Notes (Box 59, Folder 20)
    - James Joyce, Research material (Box 59, Folder 21)
    - Juvenile
    - A Christmas Treat, Notebook (Box 59, Folder 22)
    - The Dazzle, TS (Box 59, Folder 23)
  - Scripts, 1962-1987, Subseries 3.3; Boxes 60-78
    - Maud Gonne Series
    - Beloved, MS and TS (Box 60, Folder 1)
    - Beloved, TS (Box 60, Folder 2)
    - Beloved, TS (Box 60, Folder 3)
    - Beloved, TS (Box 60, Folder 4)
    - Beloved, TS (Box 60, Folder 5)
    - Beloved, TS (Box 60, Folder 6)
    - Beloved, TS (Box 60, Folder 7)
    - Beloved, TS (Box 60, Folder 8)
    - Beloved, TS (Box 60, Folder 9)
    - Beloved, TS (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - Castle of Heroes, MS (Box 61, Folder 2)
    - Castle of Heroes, TS (Box 61, Folder 3)
    - Castle of Heroes, TS (Box 61, Folder 4)
    - Castle of Heroes, TS (Box 61, Folder 5)
    - Castle of Heroes, TS (Box 61, Folder 6)
    - Castle of Heroes, TS (Box 61, Folder 7)
    - Dance With Me in Ireland, TS (Box 61, Folder 8)
    - Faerie Queen, TS (Box 61, Folder 9)
    - Faerie Queen, TS (Box 61, Folder 10)
    - "Innisfree," MS and TS (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - "Innisfree," TS (Box 62, Folder 2)
    - Maud Gonne, Notebooks (Box 62, Folder 3)
    - Maud Gonne, Notebook (Box 62, Folder 4)
    - Maud Gonne, Notebook (Box 62, Folder 5)
    - Maud Gonne, MS (Box 62, Folder 6)
    - Maud Gonne, MS and TS (Box 62, Folder 7)
    - Maud Gonne, TS (Box 62, Folder 8)
    - Maud Gonne, TS (Box 62, Folder 9)
    - Maud Gonne, TS (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - Maud Gonne, TS (Box 63, Folder 2)
    - Maud Gonne, Notes (Box 63, Folder 3)
    - Maud Gonne, Research material (Box 63, Folder 4)
    - "Maud Gonne – Woman of Destiny," (Screen Adaptation) TS (Box 63, Folder 5)
    - "Maud Gonne – Woman of Destiny," (Screen Adaptation) TS (Box 63, Folder 6)
    - "Maud Gonne – Woman of Destiny," (Screen Adaptation) TS (Box 63, Folder 7)
    - "Maud Gonne – Woman of Destiny," (Screen Adaptation) TS (Box 64, Folder 1)
    - "Maud Gonne – Woman of Destiny," (Screen Adaptation) TS (Box 64, Folder 2)
    - "Maud Gonne – Woman of Destiny," (Screen Adaptation) TS (Box 64, Folder 3)
    - "Maud Gonne – Woman of Destiny," (Screen Adaptation) bound TS (Box 64, Folder 4)
    - "Song of Love," TS (Box 64, Folder 5)
    - "Woman of the Sidhe," TS (Box 64, Folder 6)
    - "Woman of the Sidhe," TS (Box 65, Folder 1)
    - "A Young Woman and Old," TS (Box 65, Folder 2)
    - "A Young Woman and Old," TS (Box 65, Folder 3)
    - "A Young Woman and Old," TS (Box 65, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified (Box 65, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified (Box 65, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified (Box 65, Folder 7)
    - Plays
    - A Cheap Bunch of Nice Flowers (1962)
    - A Cheap Bunch of Nice Flowers, TS (Box 66, Folder 1)
    - A Cheap Bunch of Nice Flowers, TS (Box 66, Folder 2)
    - A Cheap Bunch of Nice Flowers, TS (Box 66, Folder 3)
    - A Cheap Bunch of Nice Flowers, TS (Box 66, Folder 4)
    - A Cheap Bunch of Nice Flowers, TS (Box 66, Folder 5)
    - A Pagan Place (1972)
    - A Pagan Place, TS (Box 66, Folder 6)
    - The Ladies (1975)
    - The Ladies, TS [variant title: The Women] (Box 66, Folder 7)
    - Virginia (1980)
    - Virginia, Notebooks (Box 66, Folder 8)
    - Virginia, MS (Box 66, Folder 9)
    - Virginia, TS (Box 66, Folder 10)
    - Virginia, TS (Box 67, Folder 1)
    - Virginia, Proof (Box 67, Folder 2)
    - Virginia, Notes (Box 67, Folder 3)
    - Madame Bovary (1987)
    - Madame Bovary, Notebook (Box 67, Folder 4)
    - Madame Bovary, MS (Box 67, Folder 5)
    - Madame Bovary, TS (Box 67, Folder 6)
    - Madame Bovary, TS (Box 67, Folder 7)
    - Unpublished plays
    - "Along the Arno," TS (Box 68, Folder 1)
    - "The Cut," TS (Box 68, Folder 2)
    - "The Cut," TS (Box 68, Folder 3)
    - "Glow Worms," TS (Box 68, Folder 4)
    - "Glow Worms," TS (Box 68, Folder 5)
    - "I'll Shoot Your Dog if you Don't," TS (Box 68, Folder 6)
    - "Irish Revel," TS (Box 68, Folder 7)
    - "Looking for a Man and Not a Mouse," TS (Box 68, Folder 8)
    - "The Married Woman," TS (Box 68, Folder 9)
    - "Sadism," TS (Box 68, Folder 10)
    - "Stag," TS (Box 68, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified (Box 68, Folder 12)
    - Screenplays
    - The Wicked Lady (1979)
    - The Wicked Lady, TS (Box 69, Folder 1)
    - The Wicked Lady, TS (Box 69, Folder 2)
    - The Wicked Lady, TS (Box 69, Folder 3)
    - The Country Girls (1984)
    - The Country Girls, TS (Box 69, Folder 4)
    - The Country Girls, TS (Box 69, Folder 5)
    - Unpublished screenplays
    - The Broken Doll's House, TS (Box 69, Folder 6)
    - Brother, Notebook (Box 69, Folder 7)
    - Brother, MS (Box 69, Folder 8)
    - Brother, TS (Box 69, Folder 9)
    - Burning Skies, TS (Box 70, Folder 1)
    - Burning Skies, TS (Box 70, Folder 2)
    - Burning Skies, TS (Box 70, Folder 3)
    - Collette, TS (Box 70, Folder 4)
    - Collette, TS (Box 70, Folder 5)
    - Dracula's Daughter, TS (Box 70, Folder 6)
    - Evening Flight, TS (Box 71, Folder 1)
    - Evening Flight, TS (Box 71, Folder 2)
    - Evening Flight, TS (Box 71, Folder 3)
    - Down by the River, Notebook (Box 71, Folder 4)
    - Down by the River, MS and TS (Box 71, Folder 5)
    - Down by the River, MS and TS (Box 71, Folder 6)
    - Down by the River, TS (Box 72, Folder 1)
    - Down by the River, TS (Box 72, Folder 2)
    - Down by the River, TS (Box 72, Folder 3)
    - Down by the River, Proof (Box 72, Folder 4)
    - Down by the River, Proof (Box 72, Folder 5)
    - Etty, Notebook (Box 72, Folder 6)
    - Etty, MS and TS (Box 72, Folder 7)
    - Etty, TS (Box 73, Folder 1)
    - Etty, Research material (Box 73, Folder 2)
    - Girls in their Married Bliss, TS (Box 73, Folder 3)
    - Girls in their Married Bliss, TS (Box 73, Folder 4)
    - Girls in their Married Bliss, TS (Box 73, Folder 5)
    - Girls in their Married Bliss, TS (Box 73, Folder 6)
    - Girls in their Married Bliss, TS (Box 73, Folder 7)
    - Girls in their Married Bliss, TS (Box 74, Folder 1)
    - Joan of Arc, TS (Box 74, Folder 2)
    - Kerry Babies, TS (Box 74, Folder 3)
    - Kerry Babies, Photocopy (Box 74, Folder 4)
    - Kerry Babies, Photocopy (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - Kerry Babies, Photocopy (Box 74, Folder 6)
    - Love's Tender Fury, TS (Box 74, Folder 7)
    - The Love Object, TS (Box 74, Folder 8)
    - Mary the Maid, TS (Box 74, Folder 9)
    - Once Upon a Summer, TS (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - Paradise, TS (Box 75, Folder 2)
    - Paradise, TS Bound (Box 75, Folder 3)
    - The Rack, Notebook (Box 75, Folder 4)
    - The Rack, TS (Box 75, Folder 5)
    - Riding Horse with Ivan McTaggert, TS (Box 75, Folder 6)
    - A Sailor Each, TS (Box 75, Folder 7)
    - Stag, TS (Box 75, Folder 8)
    - Stag, TS (Box 75, Folder 9)
    - Stag, TS (Box 76, Folder 1)
    - Summer Lightning, TS (Box 76, Folder 2)
    - Summer Lightning, TS (Box 76, Folder 3)
    - Sylvia Plath, Notebook (Box 76, Folder 4)
    - Sylvia Plath, MS and TS (Box 76, Folder 5)
    - The Three Piece Suite, TS (Box 76, Folder 6)
    - We, TS (Box 76, Folder 7)
    - We, TS (Box 76, Folder 8)
    - The Wooing of Miss Watson, TS (Box 76, Folder 9)
    - Teleplays
    - The Wedding Dress (1963)
    - The Wedding Dress, TS (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - The Keys to the Cafe (1965)
    - The Keys of the Café, TS (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - Which of These Two Ladies Is He Married To? (1967)
    - Which of These Two Ladies Is He Married To?, Camera script (Box 77, Folder 3)
    - Nothing's Ever Over (1968)
    - Nothing's Ever Over, TS (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - Nothing's Ever Over, Rehearsal script (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - Mrs. Reinhardt, from Her Own Story (1981)
    - Mrs. Reinhardt from Her Own Story, Notebook (Box 77, Folder 6)
    - Mrs. Reinhardt from Her Own Story, TS (Box 77, Folder 7)
    - Unpublished Teleplays
    - Mektoub, TS (Box 77, Folder 8)
    - The Messenger, TS (Box 78, Folder 1)
    - The Messenger, TS (Box 78, Folder 2)
    - Three Piece Suite, TS (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - Vanity Fair, MS and TS (Box 78, Folder 4)
- Writings by others, Series 4; Boxes 79-81
  Series 4 contains O'Brien's collection of manuscripts and typscripts by other writers. Present are critical writings and poetry about O'Brien as well as creative work by other writers, including Harold Pinter and O'Brien's son, Carlo Gebler. This series is arranged alphabetically by author, or by title when the author is unknown.
  Organized into three subseries: (4.1) Writings about Edna O'Brien, (4.2) Poems by others, and (4.3) Prose by others.
  - Writings about O'Brien, Subseries 4.1; Box 79
    - Baird, Joan, Edna O'Brien: Annotated Checklist Bibliography and Handbook, TS (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - Baird, Joan, Edna O'Brien: Annotated Checklist Bibliography and Handbook, TS (Box 79, Folder 2)
    - Bones, Gregory E., "Exile as Place in the Writing of Edna O'Brien," TS (Box 79, Folder 3)
    - Desmond, George, "Edna Observed...," TS (Box 79, Folder 4)
    - Jong, Erica, "Interview with Edna O'Brien," TS (Box 79, Folder 5)
    - Knowles, Nancy, "Exiled to the Garden: Garden Imagery in Selections from Edna O'Brien's A Fanatic Heart," TS (Box 79, Folder 6)
    - Mill, Heather, Through Fresh Eyes: Edna O'Brien and the Fanatic Art of Revision, TS (Box 79, Folder 7)
    - Pearce, Sandra Manoogian, "An Interview with Edna O'Brien," TS (Box 79, Folder 8)
    - Pearce, Sandra Manoogian,"Edna O'Brien's 'Lantern Slides' and Joyce's 'The Dead': Shadows of a Bygone Era," TS (Box 79, Folder 9)
    - Pearce, Sandra Manoogian, "Redemption through Reconciliation: Edna O'Brien's Isolated Women," TS (Box 79, Folder 10)
    - Rigg, Patricia, Censored Female Authorship: Edna O'Brien and the Legacy of Irishness, TS (Box 79, Folder 11)
    - Sclafer, Benedikte, The Quest for Identity in Edna O'Brien's Latest Novels, TS (Box 79, Folder 12)
    - Walsh, Erin, "Edna O'Brien and Irish Women as Love Objects," TS (Box 79, Folder 13)
    - Weber, Judith, "The Works of Edna O'Brien," TS (Box 79, Folder 14)
  - Poems by others, Subseries 4.2; Box 80: folders 1-23
    - Blok, Alexander, "May," TS (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - Blok, Alexander, "Parting," TS (Box 80, Folder 2)
    - Eaton, K.A., "Lost!," TS (Box 80, Folder 3)
    - Godbert, Geoffrey, "Nolde," TS (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - Gray, Alexander, "The Grave of Love," TS (Box 80, Folder 5)
    - Merryman, Bryan, "Extract from the Midnight Court," TS (Box 80, Folder 6)
    - O'Connell, Patricia, "Nellie," TS (Box 80, Folder 7)
    - O'Connell, Patricia, "To My Mother," TS (Box 80, Folder 8)
    - Orlean, Rene-Oliver, "Yeats at Lunch," TS (Box 80, Folder 9)
    - Pinter, Harold, "All of That," TS (Box 80, Folder 10)
    - Pinter, Harold, "Death," TS (Box 80, Folder 11)
    - Pinter, Harold, "The Doing So," TS (Box 80, Folder 12)
    - Pinter, Harold, "Message," TS (Box 80, Folder 13)
    - Pinter, Harold, "You Love Me Now," TS (Box 80, Folder 14)
    - Pinter, Harold, untitled (Box 80, Folder 15)
    - Rainsford, John, "To a Splendidly Imperfect Lady, called Edna O'Brien," TS (Box 80, Folder 16)
    - Schmidt, Will, "No, Nora, No!," TS (Box 80, Folder 17)
    - Williams, Mark, "Sung Silence," TS (Box 80, Folder 18)
    - Unidentified Author
    - "The Blackbird by Belfast Lough," TS (Box 80, Folder 19)
    - "Death," TS (Box 80, Folder 20)
    - "Nora," TS (Box 80, Folder 21)
    - "Truth," TS (Box 80, Folder 22)
    - Unidentified (Box 80, Folder 23)
  - Prose by others, Subseries 4.3; Box 80: folders 24-33 - Box 81
    - Dunn, Nell, First Love, TS (Box 80, Folder 24)
    - Finnegan, Seamus, Les Mouettes, TS (Box 80, Folder 25)
    - Friedman, Bruce Jay, "A Change of Plan," TS (Box 80, Folder 26)
    - Gebler, Carlos, "Watch with Parents," TS (Box 80, Folder 27)
    - Pinter, Harold, Betrayal, TS (Box 80, Folder 28)
    - Pinter, Harold, Lolita, TS (Box 80, Folder 29)
    - Pinter, Harold, Monologue, TS (Box 80, Folder 30)
    - Pinter, Harold, Mountain Language, TS (Box 80, Folder 31)
    - Pinter, Harold, Oh, Superman, TS (Box 80, Folder 32)
    - Pinter, Harold, Party Time, TS (Box 80, Folder 33)
    - Pinter, Harold, The Trial, TS (Box 81, Folder 1)
    - Southe, Robert, "Select Works of the British Poets from Chaucer to Jonson," MS (Box 81, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified (Box 81, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified Author
    - "Harmony," TS (Box 81, Folder 4)
    - "The Madman," MS (Box 81, Folder 5)
- Subject files, 1944-1999, Series 5; Boxes 82-83, OP 2-3
  The series contains the personal files of Edna O'Brien. Some of the files, such as the papers from Grayshot Hall Health Centre, Leashold Enfranchisement Association, and University of California, Irvine, were arranged by O'Brien, while others were artificially assembled out of similar materials found throughout the collection. Of particular interest in this series are O'Brien's awards, divorce papers, and memorial service programmes (including programmes for the memorial services of Robert Graves and Laurence Olivier).
  Special restrictions apply: Some material is closed to researchers.
  - Awards, Honors, and Appearances (Box 82, Folder 1)
  - Awards, Honors, and Appearances: Irish Post/Allied Banks Community Award, 1980 (Box OP2)
  - Awards, Honors, and Appearances: Honorary Doctorate, Queens University Belfast (Box OP3)
  - Contracts, 1961-1968 (Box 82, Folder 2)
  - Contracts, 1969-1986 (Box 82, Folder 3)
  - Contracts, 1992-1999 (Box 82, Folder 4)
  - Curriculum vitae (Box 82, Folder 5)
  - Divorce papers (Box 82, Folder 6)
  - Drawings (Box 82, Folder 7)
  - English Stage Society (Box 82, Folder 8)
  - Financial papers (Box 83, Folder 1)
  - Grayshot Hall Health Centre (Box 83, Folder 2)
  - Lease papers (Box 83, Folder 3)
  - Leasehold Enfranchisement Association (Box 83, Folder 4)
  - Memorial service programmes (Box 83, Folder 5)
  - Property sale (Box 83, Folder 6)
  - School papers, Carlo and Sasha [1 of 4] (Box 83, Folder 7)
  - School papers, Carlo and Sasha [2 of 4] (Box 83, Folder 8)
  - School papers, Carlo and Sasha [3 of 4] (Box 83, Folder 9)
  - School papers, Carlo and Sasha [4 of 4] (Box 83, Folder 10)
  - Tribute to Fathers O'Brien (Box 83, Folder 11)
  - University of California, Irvine (Box 83, Folder 12)
  - Will and Testament of Edna O'Brien [Restricted] (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Will and Testament [Michael and Helena O'Brien and Ernest Gebler] (Box 83, Folder 13)
- Printed material, 1958-1999, Series 6; Boxes 84-91, OP4-16
  The Edna O'Brien papers include many collected publications--clippings and entire magazines and journals--with material by or about O'Brien. These printed materials have been arranged chronologically by type: writings by O'Brien, writings about O'Brien, and other collected printed material.
  Organized into three subseries: (6.1) Writings by Edna O'Brien, (6.2) Writings about Edna O'Brien, and (6.3) Other collected printed material.
  - Writings by O'Brien, 1960-1999, Subseries 6.1; Box 84 - Box 85: folder 18
    - Publications with poems
    - "Back," in The Listener, 25 May 1972 (Box 84, Folder 1)
    - "Goodbye," in The Listener, 25 May 1972 [see Subseries 6.1, Writings by O'Brien, "Back"]
    - "Moment," in The Listener, 25 May 1972 [see Subseries 6.1, Writings by O'Brien, "Back"]
    - "Shame," in The Listener, 25 May 1972 [see Subseries 6.1, Writings by O'Brien, "Back"]
    - Publications with prose [fiction]
    - "Baby Blue," in The New Yorker, 9 June 1975 (Box 84, Folder 2)
    - from The Country Girls, in Harper's Bazaar, January 1960 (Box 84, Folder 3)
    - from The Country Girls, in You, 15 October 1995 (Box 84, Folder 4)
    - "Epitaph," in The New Yorker, 27 April, 1987 (Box 84, Folder 5)
    - from Girl with Green Eyes, in London Evening Standard, 11-15 May, 1964 (Box 84, Folder 6)
    - "Good Friday," in Ireland Today, 25 April, 1958 (Box 84, Folder 7)
    - "Irish Revel," Travelman Short Stories, 1998 (Box 84, Folder 8)
    - "A Long Way From Home," in Redbook, May 1985 (Box 84, Folder 9)
    - "Love's Lesson," in Zoetrope: All Story, Summer 1998 (Box 84, Folder 10)
    - "No Place," in Literary Switch, November 1991 (Box 84, Folder 11)
    - "The Return," in The New Yorker, 2 February, 1981 (Box 84, Folder 12)
    - "A Scandalous Woman," in The New Review, April 1974 (Box 84, Folder 13)
    - "Sin," in The New Yorker, 11 July 1994 (Box 84, Folder 14)
    - "Sin" (Box 84, Folder 15)
    - "Soeurs," in La Serpent a Plumes, Spring 1999 (Box 84, Folder 16)
    - "Violets," in The New Yorker, 5 November, 1979 (Box 84, Folder 17)
    - "Wilderness," in The New Yorker, 16 March, 1992 (Box 84, Folder 18)
    - Publications with prose [nonfiction]
    - "The Artist and His Country," in Vogue, 1 September 1971 (Box 84, Folder 19)
    - "Casualties all..." (Box 84, Folder 20)
    - "Caught Between Writing and Life," in The Observer, 22 August 1982 (Box 84, Folder 21)
    - "The Country Girls," 1981 (Box 84, Folder 22)
    - "Dear Mr. Joyce" (Box 84, Folder 23)
    - "Dear Tony Blair" (Box 84, Folder 24)
    - "Edna O'Brien is Compelled by the Dark Sensibility of William Faulkner," in Books, 1 September 1996 (Box 84, Folder 25)
    - "Edna O'Brien on Ambition," in The Independent Magazine, 28 August 1993 (Box 84, Folder 26)
    - "Edna O'Brien: Return to County Clare," in Sunday Times Magazine, 12 July 1964 (Box 84, Folder 27)
    - "Find the Solution?," in Daily Mail, 2 February 1995 (Box 84, Folder 28)
    - "Gerry Adams and the Path to Peace," in The New York Times, February 1994 (Box 84, Folder 29)
    - "Getting Even With Flaubert," in The New York Times Book Review [Review of Louise Colet's A View of Him] (Box 84, Folder 31)
    - "The Ghosts of Taste," in Gourmet, November 1999 (Box 84, Folder 32)
    - "Going Solo," in Conde Nast Traveler, March 1991 (Box 85, Folder 1)
    - "Guilt is the Big Black Monster of Love," in The Sun, 13 February 1979 (Box 85, Folder 2)
    - "In My View," in The Sunday Times, 18 March 1990 (Box 85, Folder 3)
    - "It's a Bad Time Out There for Emotion, in The New York Times Book Review, 14 February 1993 (Box 85, Folder 4)
    - "James Joyce's Women," in Harper's, September 1980 (Box 85, Folder 5)
    - "Life of O'Brien," in The Observer Review, 7 November 1999 (Box 85, Folder 6)
    - "Love and Punishment," in The Observer, 13 February 1983 (Box 85, Folder 7)
    - "Lunch with Mr. Joyce," in The Irish Times, 20 September 1983 (Box 85, Folder 8)
    - "The Madness of Love" [review of French Lieutenant's Woman] (Box 85, Folder 9)
    - Review of Toni Morrison's Jazz (Box 85, Folder 10)
    - "Samuel Beckett at 80" (Box 85, Folder 11)
    - "She Stoops but Fails to Conquer," in The Observer (Box 85, Folder 12)
    - "She Was the Other Ireland," in The New York Times Book Review, 19 June 1988 [Review of Brenda Maddox's Nora: The Real Life of Molly Bloom] (Box 85, Folder 13)
    - "The Strange World of Carson McCullers," in Books and Bookmen, October 1961 (Box 85, Folder 14)
    - "Telephone" (Box 85, Folder 15)
    - "Top Ten," in Women's Review (Box 85, Folder 16)
    - "Twisted Talk, Ulster's War," in The New York Times, 25 January 1997 (Box 85, Folder 17)
    - "Why Irish Heroines Don't Have to Be Good Anymore," in The New York Times Review (Box 85, Folder 18)